University of California, Berkeley. Department of Genetics Collection 1911-1947 Mss.378.794.C12gen
American Philosophical Society
University of California, Berkeley. Department of Genetics Collection
1911-1947
Mss.378.794.C12gen
American Philosophical Society
0.5 Linear feet
In 1912, the University of California, Berkeley, became the first university in the nation to form a separate Department of Genetics. The first two appointments in the department went to plant geneticists Ernest Brown Babcock and Roy E. Clausen, and as the department grew slowly, shifting slightly away from its roots in agricultural science, it gained a strong reputation as an important center for research in several areas in genetics and evolutionary biology. The U.C. Berkeley Department of Genetics Collection contains a selective sampling of correspondence relating to the organization and early history of the nation's first Department of Genetics. Centered in the years 1912-1930, the collection consists primarily of correspondence to and from Babcock and Clausen, pertaining to their research, administrative matters, and the genetical community. Prominent among their correspondents are George H. Shull, Thomas Hunt Morgan, A. H. Sturtevant, and H. J. Muller.
Bibliography
Babcock, Ernest Brown and Roy Elwood Clausen, Genetics in Relation to Agriculture (N.Y., 1918). Call no.: 575.13 B11g.
Babcock, Ernest Brown and J. L. Collins, Genetics Laboratory Manual (N.Y., 1918). Call no.: 575.1 B11s.
Genetics Note
This collection contains materials which relate to the history of genetics.
Agar, Wilfred Eade Correspondence (1 item) 1947
Babcock, Ernest Brown Correspondence (53 items) 1906-1948
Babcock, Ernest Brown -- Genetics I - lecture notes, course outline Manuscripts (2 items) 1914-1915
Castle, William Ernest -- Memorandum on the beginning of Genetic Studies at Harvard University, 1901-1915 Manuscripts (8 pages) Circa 1915
Clausen, Roy Elwood Correspondence (6 items) 1919-1936
Morgan, Thomas Hunt Correspondence (40 items) 1917-1932
Muller, Hermann Joseph Correspondence (13 items) 1920-1942
Shull, George Harrison Correspondence (38 items) 1911-1944
Sturtevant, Alfred Henry Correspondence (7 items) 1921-1934
Existence and Location of Copies note
The Collection has been microfilmed (Film 1441).
Other Finding Aids note
The U.C. Berkeley Department of Genetics Collection is also described in Bentley Glass's A Guide to the Genetics Collections of the APS.
Related Archival Materials note
Babcock appears as a correspondent in the papers of Milislav Demerec (B D394) and Albert Blakeslee (B B585).
The Bancroft Library at the University of California, Berkeley, houses an additional 2 feet of papers of Ernest Brown Babcock.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Gift of the University of California, Berkeley, Department of Genetics, March 1967.
Scope and Contents note
The U.C. Berkeley Department of Genetics Collection contains a selective sampling of correspondence relating to the organization, early history, and research of the nation's first Department of Genetics. Centered in the years 1912-1930, the collection consists primarily of correspondence to and from the founding members of the department, Ernest Brown Babcock and Roy E. Clausen, pertaining to their research interests, administrative matters, and the genetical community. Prominent among their correspondents are George H. Shull, Thomas Hunt Morgan, A. H. Sturtevant, and H. J. Muller.
Babcock appears to have had a particularly close relationship with George H. Shull, and their correspondence forms by far the most extensive part of the collection. Although Babcock was unsucessful in his attempt to win an appointment for Shull at Berkeley, the two maintained a close scientific correspondence, discussing their work in plant breeding, cytogenetics, and the relative status of botanical and animal genetics. In November 1944, Shull sent a lengthy autobiographical letter to Babcock, who was then considering writing a history of genetics.
Centered largely on Drosophila, the correspondence from Morgan, Muller, and Sturtevant is somewhat less extensive, but nevertheless interesting for reconstructing aspects of that research as well as the relations between the department at Berkeley and the groups at Columbia and later Cal Tech. In 1926, Morgan was one of those who intervened with Babcock to secure a position for John Belling, recovering from a bout of "acute melancholia."
Among the interesting miscellaneous items is a letter from the Australian geneticist, W. E. Agar (regarding the largely negative influence of his former advisor, William Bateson), an outline and course notes from Babcock's course in genetics, 1915, and William E. Castle's autobiographical "Memorandum on the beginning of Genetic Studies at Harvard University, 1901-1915." Also of note is a letter from Babcock to A. Franklin Shull, Feb. 6, 1934, in which Babcock makes the prescient suggestion that they organize a symposium to investigate "whether anything can be done in the way of interpreting the paleontological processes in terms of modern genetical concepts," and to discuss the integration of genetics and evolutionary processes in plants and animals.
The collection is organized alphabetically by writer, and then alphabetically by correspondent.
Biographical/Historical note
In the early days of Mendelian genetics, the University of California, Berkeley, became the first university in the nation to establish a separate Department of Genetics. Ernest B. Babcock, an assistant professor of agricultural education who had pioneered a course in plant and animal breeding in 1912, was selected to head the new department in July 1913, and after receiving his PhD in May 1914, Roy E. Clausen was appointed as his assistant.
Initially, the thrust of research in the department centered on Babcock's interest in plant breeding and the evolution of the genus Crepis and Clausen's in the genus Nicotiana, however by the 1920s, members of the department were involved in research on biosystematics, the genetics of Drosophila, cytogenetics, and radiation genetics. Babcock and Clausen co-authored a volume Genetics in Relation to Agriculture (1918, 2nd ed. 1927). Both Babcock and Clausen were elected to the National Academy of Sciences.
Five of the 11 faculty members of the department were elected to the National Academy of Sciences, and four were chosen Faculty Research Lecturers. The department was eventually absorbed into the Department of Integrative Biology.
Agar, Wilfred Eade, 1882-1951; Bateson, William, 1861-1926; Castle, William E., (William Ernest), 1867-1962; Clausen, Roy Elwood, 1891-1956; Harvard University. Department of Genetics; International Congress of Genetics(7th: 1937: Moscow); Morgan, Thomas Hunt, 1866-1945; Muller, H. J., (Hermann Joseph), 1890-1967; Navashin, Mikhail S.; Shull, A. Franklin, (Aaron Franklin), 1881-; Shull, George Harrison, 1874-1954; Sturtevant, A. H., (Alfred Henry), 1891-1970; Voorhies, E. C.; Drosophila--Genetics; Genetics; Plant breeding; Plant genetics; Radiogenetics
- Correspondence, 1911-1947 (Box 1)
  - Letter to Ernest Brown Babcock, on "Bateson's influence", 1947; 1 item; Agar, Wilfred Eade, 1882-1951
    Bateson, William N.; Biographical and personal data; Graduate study; History of biology, especially genetics; University of California, Berkeley
  - Babcock, Ernest Brown, 1906-1948; 53 items
    Bibliographical matters; Conferences and symposia; Cytogenetics; Evolution; Genetics; Genetics of plants; History of biology, especially genetics; Johannsen, Wilhelm; Lectures, public speaking; Morgan, Thomas Hunt; Muller, Hermann Joseph; Publication; Recommendations -- Clausen, Roy Elwood; Shull, George Harrison; Teaching; Travel -- Invitations, arrangements; University of California, Berkeley
    - Bibliography, 1906-1945; 1 item; Babcock, E. B. (Ernest Brown), b. 1877
    - Diary of European travel, 1919; 1 item; Babcock, E. B. (Ernest Brown), b. 1877
    - Genetics I, 1914-1915; 2 folders
      Genetics; Teaching; University of California, Berkeley; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.
      - Genetics I (course outline), 1914-1915; 1 item; Babcock, E. B. (Ernest Brown), b. 1877
      - Genetics I (lecture notes), 1914-1915; 1 item; Babcock, E. B. (Ernest Brown), b. 1877
    - Letter to C. Leonard Huskins, 1948; 1 item; Babcock, E. B. (Ernest Brown), b. 1877
    - Letter to E. D. Merrill, 1928; 2 items; Babcock, E. B. (Ernest Brown), b. 1877
    - Letter to Thomas Hunt Morgan, 1917-1926; 11 items; Babcock, E. B. (Ernest Brown), b. 1877
    - Letter to H. J. Muller, 1920-1936; 6 items; Babcock, E. B. (Ernest Brown), b. 1877
    - Letter to Mikhail S. Navashin, 1927; 1 item; Babcock, E. B. (Ernest Brown), b. 1877
    - Letter to A. Franklin Shull, 1934; 2 items; Babcock, E. B. (Ernest Brown), b. 1877
    - Letter to George H. Shull, 1911-1942; 24 items; Babcock, E. B. (Ernest Brown), b. 1877
    - Letter to U.S. Secretary of State, 1927; 1 item; Babcock, E. B. (Ernest Brown), b. 1877
      Scope and Contents note
      Re: Mikhail Navashin's visa.
    - Letter to E. C. Voorhies, 1923; 2 items; Babcock, E. B. (Ernest Brown), b. 1877
    - Translation of W. Johannsen, Elemente des Exakten Erblichkeitslehre, n.d.; 1 item; Babcock, E. B. (Ernest Brown), b. 1877
  - Letter to Thomas Hunt Morgan, 1920; 1 items; Bateson, William
  - Memorandum on the beginning of genetic studies at Harvard, 1901-1915, Circa 1915; 8 pages; Castle, William E., (William Ernest), 1867-1962
    Bibliographical matters; Drosophila genetics; Educational matters; Genetics; Harvard University; Mendel, Gregor; Rabbit genetics; Rat genetics
  - Clausen, Roy Elwood, 1919-1936; 6 items
    Babcock, Ernest Brown; Drosophila genetics; Educational matters -- Research programs; Genetics; Genetics of plants; Graduate study; Morgan, Thomas Hunt; Muller, Hermann Joseph; Sturtevant, Alfred Henry; University of California, Berkeley
    - Letter to Ernest Brown Babcock, n.d.; 1 item; Clausen, Roy Elwood, 1891-1956
    - Letter to C. B. Lipman, 1941; 1 item (with encl.); Clausen, Roy Elwood, 1891-1956
    - Letter to Thomas Hunt Morgan, 1919, 1927; 2 items; Clausen, Roy Elwood, 1891-1956
    - Letter to H. J. Muller, 1936; 1 item; Clausen, Roy Elwood, 1891-1956
    - Letter to A. H. Sturtevant, 1932; 1 item; Clausen, Roy Elwood, 1891-1956
  - Letter to Ernest Brown Babcock, 1911; 2 items; Griffiths, F. T.
  - Letter to Ernest Brown Babcock, 1948; 1 item; Huskins, C. L.
  - Letter to E. C. Voorhies, 1923; 1 item; Hutchinson, C. B.
  - Letter to Ernest Brown Babcock, 1936; 1 item; Levit, S. G.
  - Letter to Ernest Brown Babcock, 1948-1949; 2 items; Miyabe, Knigo
  - Morgan, Thomas Hunt, 1917-1932; 40 items
    Babcock, Ernest Brown; Drosophila genetics; Goldschmidt, Richard Benedict; Publication; Recommendations -- Belling, John; University of California, Berkeley
    - Corrections..., n.d.; 1 item; Morgan, Thomas Hunt, 1866-1945
    - Letters to Ernest Brown Babcock, 1917-1927; 24 items; Morgan, Thomas Hunt, 1866-1945
    - Letters to Roy E. Clausen, 1919-1932; 7 items; Morgan, Thomas Hunt, 1866-1945
    - Letters to J. L. Collins, 1918; 3 items; Morgan, Thomas Hunt, 1866-1945
    - Letter to Cullen, 1918; 1 item; Morgan, Thomas Hunt, 1866-1945
    - Letter to Ginn and Co., 1917; 1 item; Morgan, Thomas Hunt, 1866-1945
    - Letter to Dr. Haring, 1921; 1 item; Morgan, Thomas Hunt, 1866-1945
    - Letter to McGraw Hill Book Co., 1926; 1 items; Morgan, Thomas Hunt, 1866-1945
    - Letter to Merriam, 1917; 1 item; Morgan, Thomas Hunt, 1866-1945
  - Muller, Hermann Joseph, 1920-1942; 13 items
    Babcock, Ernest Brown; Clausen, Roy Elwood; Drosophila genetics; International Congress of Genetics -- Seventh Congress; Recommendations -- Redfield, Helen; University of California, Berkeley
    - Letters to Ernest Brown Babcock, 1920-1942; 9 items; Muller, H. J., (Hermann Joseph), 1890-1967
    - Letters to Roy E. Clausen, 1923-1936; 4 items; Muller, H. J., (Hermann Joseph), 1890-1967
  - Letter to Roy E. Clausen, 1937; 1 item; Muralov, A. and N. I. Vavilov
  - Letters to Ernest Brown Babcock, 1927-1929; 5 items; Navashin, Mikhail S.
  - Letter to Ernest Brown Babcock, 1926; 1 item; Sharp, Lester W., (Lester Whyland), b. 1887
  - Letter to Ernest Brown Babcock, 1934; 1 items; Shull, A. Franklin, (Aaron Franklin), 1881-
  - Shull, George Harrison, 1911-1944; 38 items
    Babcock, Ernest Brown; Biographical and personal data; Cytogenetics; Genetics of plants; History of biology, especially genetics; Johannsen, Wilhelm; Lectures, public speaking; University of California, Berkeley
    - Letters to Ernest Brown Babcock, 1911-1944; 3 folders; Shull, George Harrison, 1874-1954
      - Letters to Ernest Brown Babcock, 1911-1913; 10 items; Shull, George Harrison, 1874-1954 (Folder 1)
      - Letters to Ernest Brown Babcock, 1914-1918; 13 items; Shull, George Harrison, 1874-1954 (Folder 2)
      - Letters to Ernest Brown Babcock, 1922-1944; 9 items; Shull, George Harrison, 1874-1954 (Folder 3)
    - Letters to Roy E. Clausen, 1922; 4 items; Shull, George Harrison, 1874-1954
    - Letter to J. L. Collins, 1923; 1 item; Shull, George Harrison, 1874-1954
    - Letter to John M. Coulter, 1911; 1 item; Shull, George Harrison, 1874-1954
  - Sturtevant, Alfred Henry, 1921-1934; 7 items
    Conferences and symposia -- Eugenics; Drosophila genetics; Publication -- Genetics; Shull, George Harrison; University of California, Berkeley
    - Letters to Ernest Brown Babcock, 1930-1931; 2 items; Sturtevant, Alfred H.
    - Letters to Roy E. Clausen, 1921-1931; 3 items; Sturtevant, Alfred H.
    - Letter to J. L. Collins, 1927; 1 item; Sturtevant, Alfred H.
    - Letter to D. F. Jones, 1934; 1 item; Sturtevant, Alfred H.
  - Letter to Ernest Brown Babcock, 1923; 1 item; Voorhies, E. C.
  - Letter to Ernest Brown Babcock, 1918; 1 item; Wheeler, Benjamin I. (Benjamin Ide), 1854-1927
- Printed material, 1917-1945
  - 1822-1922. The Galton and Mendel Memorial Fund..., ca.1922; Broadside
  - Dedication of Hilgard Hall, 1917; Program
  - Five Lectures on the Hitchcock Foundation [Thomas Hunt Morgan Lectures, April 1916], Broadside
  - "Genetics", n.d.; Galley proof
  - How I Became a Geneticist, California Monthly, June-July 1945; Babcock, E. B. (Ernest Brown), b. 1877
  - McGraw-Hill [Advertisement for Babcock's Genetics in Relation to Agriculture], 1917; Broadside, 2 items